Photographs of Josefina Fierro, 1903-1987. M0784
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
Josefina Fierro photographs
1903-1987
M0784
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
2.0 Linear feet (114 photographs housed in 1 manuscript box, 1 flat box)
Photographs of Josefina Fierro, a leader in the Mexican American community.
Fierro, Josefina
Biography
Born in the border town of Mexicali, Baja California during the tumultuous years of the Mexican Revolution, Josefina Fierro was raised in a familial heritage of revolutionary activism. Her father was an officer in General Francisco "Pancho" Villa's northern revolutionary army, a fact that made him largely absent from her life. Raised by her mother, who separated from her husband and immigrated to the U.S. when Josefina was a baby, the language of revolution and social justice was a constant in her young life. Her mother's family was followers of Ricardo Flores Magon, a Mexican anarchist banished from Mexico for promoting radical reforms as part of his Partido Liberal Mexicano, a movement he continued while in exile on the U.S. side of the border. As a "Magonista," Josefina's mother taught her daughter to stand up for the underdog, to speak out against injustice, and to treat others with dignity and respect. It was no surprise that Josefina would eventually use this background as a basis for assuming leadership within the Mexican American community in California as she came of age.
Born in the border town of Mexicali, Baja California during the tumultuous years of the Mexican Revolution, Josefina Fierro was raised in a familial heritage of revolutionary activism. Her father was an officer in General Francisco "Pancho" Villa's northern revolutionary army, a fact that made him largely absent from her life. Raised by her mother, who separated from her husband and immigrated to the U.S. when Josefina was a baby, the language of revolution and social justice was a constant in her young life. Her mother's family was followers of Ricardo Flores Magon, a Mexican anarchist banished from Mexico for promoting radical reforms as part of his Partido Liberal Mexicano, a movement he continued while in exile on the U.S. side of the border. As a "Magonista," Josefina's mother taught her daughter to stand up for the underdog, to speak out against injustice, and to treat others with dignity and respect. It was no surprise that Josefina would eventually use this background as a basis for assuming leadership within the Mexican American community in California as she came of age.
Josefina's successful organizing efforts and her emergence as a key leader in the Los Angeles Mexican community attracted the attention of Latino leaders, especially Luisa Moreno, who were preparing to launch the first-ever national Latino civil rights organization, the Congress of Spanish-Speaking People. The Congress was founded in Los Angeles in 1939, and young Josefina was elected national secretary, the second highest ranking position in the organization. For the next several years, she and her colleagues led a broad-based civil rights movement for Mexican Americans and other Latinos in California and in the Southwest. A fiery orator who could captivate an audience, Josefina traveled throughout California to participate in various demonstrations and activities aimed at bringing down the walls of discrimination against Mexicans in housing, employment, education, and other public places. She played an instrumental role, in addition, on the defense committee of the infamous "Sleepy Lagoon Case" in war-time Los Angeles (a murder trial involving several Mexican American youth accused and sentenced to prison for a crime they did not commit). The Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee eventually won the release of the defendants from state prison two years after the original convictions. A year later, in June 1943, Josefina almost single-handedly brought an end to the days of rage and physical assault on Mexican Americans in downtown and in East Los Angeles during the so-called "Zoot Suit Riots." With the L.A.P.D. unwilling to stop the brutality in the streets against Mexican American youth, Josefina flew to Washington, D.C. with a Mexican consulate official to prevail upon the Vice-President of the United States, Henry Wallace, to help bring an end to the violence unleashed against her community. Convinced by her graphic, first-hand stories about the beatings of Mexican Americans by servicemen, buttressed by an armful of newspapers she carried with sensational headlines about the riots, Wallace secured a military order that restricted all service personnel to their respective bases until order was restored.
As Josefina's efforts to advocate for Mexican Americans attracted more notice, she was labeled as a "communist subversive" by the California Committee on UnAmerican Activities. After her divorce from John Bright, she returned to Madera where she organized on behalf of Henry Wallace's Independent Progressive party. By 1948, after being hounded by the FBI and fearing arrest and deportation, she decided to leave the United States and head to Hermosillo, the Mexican port city where she lived the rest of her life.
As Josefina's efforts to advocate for Mexican Americans attracted more notice, she was labeled as a "communist subversive" by the California Committee on UnAmerican Activities. After her divorce from John Bright, she returned to Madera where she organized on behalf of Henry Wallace's Independent Progressive party. By 1948, after being hounded by the FBI and fearing arrest and deportation, she decided to leave the United States and head to Hermosillo, the Mexican port city where she lived the rest of her life.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in chronologically.
Related Collection
See M0811 for interviews of Josefina Fierro by Dr. Albert M. Camarillo, Professor of History, Stanford University.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given by the donor to Stanford University, Special Collections in March 1995.
Labor history; Mexican American women; Mexican Americans--Biography; Photoprints.
- Florence, Arizona, 1917, restaurant scene with three women, no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Brothers of Arturo Arancibia, before Josefa (mother) married him. Cowboy theme/photo of three men, no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
- No description on back. High quality portrait of a young woman with short hair and necklace emblem, no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
- No description on back. Lightly printed or fading. Photo of a young woman standing holding an umbrella, no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Mandera ranch, Josefina (right) school teacher (middle) brother (far left) and mother, car behind family, ca. 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Josefina and Jocabo (cousin) Florence, Arizona, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Portrait of three children, boy, young girl, and young Josefina? (On back: ?,?, Josefina?) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Sonora Enro 23-20 Arizona, portrait of a man legs crossed, postcard, no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Brothers of Arturo Arancibia, before Josefa (mother) married him. Cowboy theme/photo of three men, no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Father and mother, Francisco Borboa, Fierro, posed with car and child under car, ca. 1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Florence, Josefina Fierro, Miss Rosalia Amador, ca. 1918 12. Paul and Josefina Fierro, Florence, Arizona, Age 6 and 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Josefina, 2 years old, Nana, postcard addressed to Roberto Amador, Calexico, CA April 22, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Josefina's only photograph of her father" postcard; signed Rosa, Calexico, CA, July 8, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Luis and Elisa Amador (wife) Guaymas, Mexico, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Paul Borva Fierro, Los Angeles, CA, postcard; Paul on front of photo ca. 1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Don Neiro (half-brother), Mother, Sister Maura, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Aunt Delz and Arthur at ranch in madders, California, no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Araniclerita Brothers, Mother's husband, Arthur Aranubia? 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Josefa's brother, ca. 1920-1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Mother and Arthur, early 1930's (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Family at ranch, ca. 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Josefa, Josefina's mother (?) 26 yrs. old, Santa Monica, CA, in a Gypsy outfit (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Paul and Josefina Fierro, Florence, Arizona, Age 6 and 7, ca.1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Benito Amador, postcard 1920: "Brother / Composer" (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Josefa Amador and Roberto Amador, ca. 1912 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Josefina, Guaymas, Mexico, December 29, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- John De Bright, portrait, Bar Music, Hollywood, ca. 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Josefina 20 Birthday, John De Bright, la Bamba Night Club, Olvera Street, Los Angeles, 1931, photo by: Hal Marty (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Josefina 21st Birthday with husband, John DeBright, photo by Hal Marty, Hollywood, CA, ca.1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Josefina (right) John De Bright (center) with Florence Hamolka, New York City, 1948, photo by: Ivan Black, on backside: Barney Josephson, Cafe Society Downtown 7/13/48 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- John De Bright, Red Cross, New York City, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- John De Bright, in car, photo by Irving Lippman, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- John De bright and Anne Sheridan, photo by Madison Lacy, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Josefina (right) with sailors (brother's good friend) and mother, Los Angeles, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- John De Bright, portrait, U.S. Coast Guard, 3rd Naval District, written on front side "In devotion and love (and some sympathy)" (Box 1, Folder 2)
- John De Bright, Red Cross, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Josefina portrait, Los Angeles, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Josefina (right) John De Bright (center) with Florence Hamolka, New York City, 1948, photo by: Ivan Black. (on backside: Barney Josephson, Cafe Society Downtown 7/13/48) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Jack Carter with Josefina, Palm Springs, 1939 2) Josefina, Palm Springs, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina, glamour portrait, New York City, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina, portrait, Los Angeles, photo by Florence Homolka, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina, New York, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina, Los Angeles, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina, Los Angeles, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina, 1940, on backside "Rushmore suggests this" (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina, Los Angeles, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina, New York, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina, 1940, photo by: Florence Homolka (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Home of where Josefina was born. ca. 1947, San Joredel Cabo, B.C.(?) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Pete Daniels, wedding night, ca.1947: dinner at Sinaloa, San Francisco, CA. with Pete's daughters, Marty and Maggie (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Peter Daniel and Josefina, San Francisco, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Peter Daniel and Josefina, San Francisco, 1948 (on back written Guaymas '1950) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Mother: Josefa Arancibia and Richard Daniel (adopted son of Josefina) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Hollywood Ten, 1950, John De Bright (right), Mexico City, Pete Daniel (left) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina and John De Bright, 2nd marriage, ca.1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina (right profile portrait) Los Angeles, 193921) Josefina (left profile portrait) 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Eva Garza (comadre) photo by: Annemarie Heinrich, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- John De Bright and Josefina (right of frame) group portrait on canal, no date (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Olachea family, Josefina (upper left) 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- No description on back, possibly a young Pete Daniel(?) holding a rooster (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina on ice skates, no date (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina with friend, ice sailboat, no date (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina at the ranch with friend in Madera, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina with small boy, no date (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina eating a hotdog. Roseluta Beach, September, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina (right) with two women, Los Angeles, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Mercedes Vda Arguello, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Josefina on shoreline, college days, Santa Monica Beach, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Paul Fierro, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Paul (Pablo) Fierro, Los Angeles, photo by Mark Studio (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Mama, 1940's (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Paul Fierro and Mae West, 1937, studio shot, Title of film "She Done Him Wrong" (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Photo by Charles Schneider, Two men, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Photo of three men with guitars, two women, one man in center, restaurant scene, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- El dia de Gracias, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Josefina and adopted daughter, Lisa, at Las Planitas, Feb, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Morin Senato, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Aunt rela Salome cousin, ca.1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Prime Salome Phillip, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Interparliamentary Convention, Gov. Alex Camarillo Macca, ca. 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Bruce Babbitt, Gov. of Arizona, Alex Carrillo Maun, Gov. of Sonora Oscarvilloa (left center), ca.1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Richard Rice Daniels, college days, Juarez, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Card for death of adopted son, ca. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- No description on back, Josefina with young girl, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Ano, Women of the Year, Josefina with flowers (center) 1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- No description on back family portrait, all women, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- No description on back Josefina with two women, dressed in traditional clothing for carnival, no date (1980?) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Josefina with her mother, Josefa, ca.l977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Josefina seated on camel, Africa, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- No description on back, family portrait outside mother seated in middle, four women, Josefina, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Josephina's mother 80 yrs old, Guaymas, Mexico (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Guaymas, Carnival parade, floats, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Guaymas, Carnival parade, floats, stamp on back: Randy Terrey 1605 Woodbury Drive, Harbor City, CA 90710, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Postcard of San Jose Del Cabo (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Picture of the harbor, no date (3 items) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Josefina with male friend at the Taberna Del Greco, mid 1970's? (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Pete Daniels, wedding night, ca.1947: dinner at Sinaloa, San Francisco, CA. with Pete's daughters, Marty and Maggie (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Josefina and Pete Daniels, possible restaurant opening? no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Josefina at La Fonda de Recunerdo, same male friend from "Taberna Del Greco" photo to left of frame, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "About a month before we opened the restaurant". Photo of a harbor with mountains in background, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Family portrait, Josefina (top left) Pete Daniels (top right) young family below, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Caterdral de Barcelona ESPANA (on front) group portrait, Josefina (in lower center of frame) no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Plate photo, Mother's family, Amadoir, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Print from plate, Mother's family, Amadoir, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Josefina, 11 years old, grammar school, ca-1923 (Flat-box 2, Folder 1)
- Josefina, portrait, photo by Florence Homolka, Los Angeles, 1942 (2 photos) (Flat-box 2, Folder 1)
- Josefina, Pete Daniels, Josefa Arancibia, Josefa, at the Capri restaurant, Mexico City, 1950 (Flat-box 2, Folder 2)
- Josefina, portrait with flowers, Guaymas, Sonora, Mexico, photo by Arturo Petsch (written on backside "with love"), 1971 (Flat-box 2, Folder 2)